Guide to the Edgar Parin and Ingri D'Aulaire Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- II. March 2006 Acquisition, 1930-1978; 14.8 linear ft. (40 boxes) + 16 film reels, 1 broadside folder, 1 roll
  - Objects
    - Personal tin boxes (Box 170)
    - Eye glasses (Box 171)
  - Audiovisual Material
    - Films
      All films are 16mm.
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - Pix and sound, Fireside (Box 172 (Cold Storage))
      - Pix and sound, Fireside (Box 173 (Cold Storage))
      - Springtime (Box 174 (Cold Storage))
      - Lunch, Vermont (Box 175 (Cold Storage))
      - Lunch, Vermont (Box 176 (Cold Storage))
      - Wild Sound (Box 177 (Cold Storage))
      - Eda, Ola, Nils, and Peter (Box 178 (Cold Storage))
      - Pix sound, Trolls first outs (Box 179 (Cold Storage))
      - Pix sound, Trolls first outs (Box 180 (Cold Storage))
      - D'Aulaire working in stone (Box 181 (Cold Storage))
      - D'Aulaire working in stone (Box 182 (Cold Storage))
      - D'Aulaire working in stone (Box 183 (Cold Storage))
      - Ingri and the baby (Box 184 (Cold Storage))
      - Nils, Ola sign (Box 185 (Cold Storage))
      - Ingri and Edgar...studio (Box 186 (Cold Storage))
      - Outdoor scenes (Box 187 (Cold Storage))
      - Weston Woods / Children of the Northlights (Box 188 (Cold Storage))
        30 minute documentary film on Ingri and Edgar D'Aulaire in their later years
    - Sound Recordings
      Produced by Weston Woods Studios
      - Don't Count Your Chicks, sound filmstrips (Box 189 (Oversize))
      - Ola, sound filmstrips with accompanying material (Box 190)
        Includes slides, booklet, and a 7 inch audiodisc
    - Other Audiovisual Materials
      - Children of the Northlights, master BetaSP videorecording, undated; 1 (Box 190, Item barcode 39002099369127)
      - Children of the Northlights, DVD copy of 16mm film (Box 190)
  - Oversize
    - Miscellaneous group of etchings, drawings, clippings, bookplate designs, proofs, Christmas cards, designs for unknown books (Box 191 (Oversize))
    - Miscellaneous leaves, pen and ink sketches, drawings (Box 191 (Oversize))
    - "Five Years of Children's Books," original watercolor, pencil drawing and proof; "Dance Little Gentleman," original pencil drawing; "Kari," original pen and ink and blue line proof (Box 191 (Oversize))
    - Color prints for unidentified book (Box 191 (Oversize))
    - Miscellaneous group possibly for end papers or covers (Box 192 (Oversize))
    - Proofs of illustrations for unidentified book (Box 192 (Oversize))
    - Signed prints of children reading book, original pencil drawing and signed prints of Arabs fighting on horseback, unsigned image (Box 192 (Oversize))
    - Miscellaneous group of proofs including a number of pirate motifs (Box 192 (Oversize))
    - Poster for Wilton Library Association: proofs in various states with cutout figures used in design (Box 192 (Oversize))
    - Poster, "Books for the World of Tomorrow," original watercolor, color proofs (Box 192 (Oversize))
    - Proofs for German books illustrated by Edgar Parin D'Aulaire (Box 192 (Oversize))
    - Book jackets (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - "The Cape-Enders" proof for dust jacket and other proofs (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - Fantasy: color illustrations and black and white drawing (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - Miscellaneous pencil drawings, and charcoal portrait, 2 (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - Original watercolor with some text written in Ingri's hand, proofs depicting Adam and Eve (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - Photos of fresco done by Edgar in main church in Norway (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - Pencil drawings and color studies of nudes by the D'Aulaires while they were students at the Hans Hoffman School in Paris (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - Mixed media drawings/sketches/studies depicting various images of New York City (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - Mixed media drawings/sketches/studies depicting various images of Norway (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - Mixed media drawings/sketches/studies depicting various images of Tunisia (Box 193 (Oversize))
    - Mixed media drawings/sketches/studies depicting various images of Norwegian children (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Colored and pencil drawings depicting various European scenes including Paris, Holland, Italy, and Germany (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Mixed media drawings/sketches/studies depicting various images of family members (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Study of head portrait of Peggy Lesser, Doubleday editor (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Early watercolors by Edgar Parin D'Aulaire (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Mixed media drawings/sketches/studies depicting various unidentified images, 3 folders (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Humorous watercolor depicting 2 figures holding a banner over a blank door (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Pencil drawings (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Drawings (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Girl with opera glasses, man sitting behind in opera box seat (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Miscellaneous sketches (Box 194 (Oversize))
    - Easel (Box 195 (Oversize))
    - Original pencil drawings, signed prints with pirate motif (Box 196 (Oversize))
    - Color prints for unidentified book (Box 196 (Oversize))
    - "Rama," pencil sketch of end paper, signed proof, proof of title, proof of dust jacket (Box 196 (Oversize))
    - Award, "Who's Who of Women" (Box 196 (Oversize))
    - Material for "The Needle in the Haystack," by Matheson (Box 196 (Oversize))
    - "Der Goldene Brunnen," original watercolors, proofs, and publisher's advertisements (Box 196 (Oversize))
    - German language books, 2 (Box 196 (Oversize))
    - Pencil drawing and salesman's sample for, "Blood," by Ewers, 1930 (Box 196 (Oversize))
    - New York Times Book Review, 1967 November 5 (Box 196 (Oversize))
    - Empty film canister, Children of the Northlights (Box 197 (Oversize))
    - Ola on rocking horse: fantasy concept original color illustration by Ingri and Edgar depicting Ola as a child on a rocking horse with figures from various books circling around him, 1 pastel, color pencil and black and white drawings (Box 198 (Broadside))
    - Print and pencil sketch (Box 199 (Roll))
- III. March 2006 Acquisition, 1930; 0.21; (1 box)
  This item was originally transferred to the Printed Acquisitions Unit of the Beinecke Library, but was subsequently returned to the collection.
  Former call number: Uncat MS Vault File.
  - Blood, by H. H. Ewers, lithographs by Edgar Parin D'Aulaire, printed version, 1930 (Box 200)
- IV. September 2007 Acquisition, 1909-1985; 9.42 linear feet (33 boxes) + 1 roll
  Organized into six groupings: Objects, Slides, Sketchbooks and Notebooks, Drawings, Painting, and Restricted Fragile.
  This portion of the collection is largely comprised of the D'Aulaires' artwork relating to several of their children's books, including Pocahontas (1946), Abraham Lincoln (1957), and Ingri and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire's Book of Greek Myths (1962), among others. Material relating to the D'Aulaires' artwork and creative process can be found in sketches, notebooks, drawings, a painting, and various objects relating to the artistic process, such as painter's palettes and other art supplies. Also included are slides and lithographic stones.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 985.
  Similar material can be found in I. February 2006 Acquisition, II. March 2006 Acquisition, and III. March 2006 Acquisition.
  Donated by Nils Daulaire and Per Ola D'Aulaire, 2007.
  Boxes 230-233 (lithograph stones): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Objects
    - Catholic Library Association Medal (Box 201)
    - Painter's Palette (Box 201)
    - Painter's Palette (metal) (Box 201)
    - Pastels Box (Box 201)
    - Box of Artist's Tools (Box 201)
  - Slides
    - Slides, 10; Sets of slides (Box 201)
  - Sketchbooks and Notebooks
    - Sketch Tablet [of people] (Box 202)
    - Sketchbook [Ingri], 1925 [?] (Box 202)
    - Tunis, Kairouan, 1928-1929 (Box 202)
    - Konigsberg, 1925 November (Box 202)
    - Bedouins (Box 202)
    - Landscapes and animals, circa 1934 (Box 202)
    - Landscapes and animals (Box 202)
    - Notebook, 1930-1933 (Box 202)
    - Accounts ledger, early 1920s (Box 203)
    - Figures, objects, etc., late 1940s-1952 (Box 203)
    - Horseback riding (Box 203)
    - Edgar Parin, Trondheim, 1909 [?] (Box 203)
    - Sketch, notebook, 1959 [?] (Box 203)
    - Loose sketches (Box 203)
    - Charcoal sketches (mostly blank) (Box 203)
    - Birds, Columbus, etc., 1954 (Box 203)
    - Figures, etc., 1955 (Box 203)
    - Sketchbook from Edgar Parin as art student (Box 204)
    - Colored sketchbook (Box 204)
    - Paris (Box 204)
    - Sketches and language notes (Box 204)
    - Edgar Parin's school notebook; art, math, chemistry (Box 204)
    - Chemistry Notes (Box 204)
    - Sketches arranged by country (Box 204)
    - Sketches by Edgar Parin's mother (Box 204)
    - Recipe book (Box 204)
    - Empty notebook (Box 205)
    - Notebook, including teachers and material on teaching; loose sketches (Box 205)
    - Travels to Puerto Rico, Martinique and Mt. Rushmore (Box 205)
    - Miscellaneous, including animals, plant life, Medieval period sketches and a motorcycle (Box 205)
    - Dummies for junior books (Box 205)
    - Loose pages, especially of trees (Box 205)
    - Sketchbook, 1913 [?] (Box 206)
    - Short story manuscript with sketches (Box 206)
    - "Dumb Men and Mischievous Wives" (Box 206)
    - Benjamin Franklin, 1947 [?] (Box 206)
    - Mostly blank notebook (Box 206)
    - Mostly blank notebook from Paris (Box 207 (Oversize))
    - Nudes (Box 207 (Oversize))
    - Female nudes (Box 207 (Oversize))
    - Landscapes, people and objects, 3 (Box 208 (Oversize))
    - Landscapes, people and objects, 4 (Box 209 (Oversize))
    - Sketches and sketchbook for mythology (Box 210 (Oversize))
    - Studies for Children of the Northlights including handwritten text drafts (Box 210 (Oversize))
    - Edda (Box 211 (Oversize))
    - Sketches of people (Box 211 (Oversize))
  - Drawings
    - Foxie (Box 212 (Oversize))
    - East of the Sun and West of the Moon (Box 212 (Oversize))
    - George Washington (Box 212 (Oversize))
    - Columbus (Box 212 (Oversize))
    - Animals Everywhere (Box 213 (Oversize))
    - Benjamin Franklin (Box 213 (Oversize))
    - Benjamin Franklin (Box 213 (Oversize))
    - "Blanche Van Buren" (Box 213 (Oversize))
    - Norse Gods and Giants, proofs (Box 214 (Oversize))
    - Norse Gods and Giants, films (Box 214 (Oversize))
    - Norse Gods and Giants (Box 214 (Oversize))
    - Wings for Per, photographs and drawings, 3 folders (Box 215 (Oversize))
    - D'Aulaires' Trolls and The Terrible Troll-Bird, numbered and signed prints, 2 (Box 216 (Oversize))
    - Children of the Northlights, 5 (Box 216 (Oversize))
      Includes proofs, doubles, studies, and original drawings.
    - Columbus, 9 folders (Box 217 (Oversize))
      Includes acetate drawings, color proofs and photostats, unbound proof in two gatherings, and hand-colored and black and white drawings
    - East of the Sun and West of the Moon (Box 218 (Oversize))
    - Foxie (Box 218 (Oversize))
    - The Magic Meadow (Box 218 (Oversize))
    - Pocahontas, 4 folders (Box 218 (Oversize))
      Includes all black keys for colors, negatives of double prints, and end papers
    - Pocahontas, 5 folders (Box 219 (Oversize))
      Includes book jacket and original color and black and white drawings, some mounted
    - Ingri and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire's Book of Greek Myths, 3 (Box 220 (Oversize))
    - Ingri and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire's Book of Greek Myths, 2 (Box 221 (Oversize))
      Includes double page acetates
    - Ingri and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire's Book of Greek Myths, 4 (Box 222 (Oversize))
      Includes single page acetates, envelopes, and box lids
    - Ingri and Edgar Parin D'Aulaire's Book of Greek Myths, 5 (Box 223 (Oversize))
      Includes single and double page acetates, envelopes and box lids
    - Don't Count Your Chicks, 2 (Box 224 (Oversize))
    - Don't Count Your Chicks, 2 folders (Box 225 (Oversize))
    - Abraham Lincoln, 4 (Box 226 (Oversize))
      Includes black acetates, key and separation, and box lids
    - Abraham Lincoln, 4 (Box 227 (Oversize))
      Includes cover acetates and stones
    - Breakfast tray with pencil drawing from D'Aulaires' Book of Animals (Box 228 (Oversize))
    - Columbus (Box 229 (Roll))
  - Painting
    - Untitle painting of wagons circled during attack, undated (Box Box 235 (Oversize))
  - Restricted Fragile
    - Lithograph stone (Box 230 (Oversize))
    - Lithograph stone (Box 231 (Oversize))
    - Lithograph stone (Box 232 (Oversize))
    - Lithograph stone (Box 233 (Oversize))